<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the query of a deist concerning the necessity of faith.</title>
            <author>J. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C51</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24111</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07951953</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07951953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40686</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40686)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1200:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the query of a deist concerning the necessity of faith.</title>
                  <author>J. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: J.C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Query of a deist.</term>
               <term>Justification.</term>
               <term>Election (Theology)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:40686:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40686:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE QUERY of a DEIST, <hi>Concerning the Neceſſity of Faith.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the Diſcourſe we had when laſt we met, you demanded of me, Whether it was not a ſhocking Sentence, and hardly conſiſtent with the Juſtice and Clemency of God, to affirm, That a Perſon born and bred in a Pagan Country, where Chriſtianity is either not at all known, or at leaſt ſo repreſented, as to render it incredible and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd; yet this Perſon living up to the dictates of a good Conſcience in Morality, that is, To the Preſcript of the Law of Nature, in regard to God, and his Neighbour, to the beſt of his knowledg; Or in caſe of frailty and failure, becoming Repentant of his fault, ſhould nevertheleſs be Damn'd for want of a Belief, (tho' contrary to his Reaſon) of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Miſteries of the Chriſtian Faith? And what you thus ſaid of an Unbeliever, you proportionably (and with Truth) adapted to an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Believer.</p>
            <p>To this (as I may term it) Antichriſtian Query, I, as a Chriſtian, return by way of Anſwer, this oppoſite Aſſertion <hi>(viz.) Salvation, as it imports either Remiſſion of Sin, or Fruition of God, is not due to Man, nor attainable by him, otherwiſe than by a right Faith in one Mediator between God and Man Chriſt Jeſus. And therefore there actually is ſuch a Mediator, and ſuch a Faith.</hi> This general Aſſertion contains ſeveral diſtinct Parts, or Poſitions, each of which I ſhall endeavour briefly to explain, and render rational to an impartial Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40686:2"/>My firſt Poſition is, That <hi>Remiſſion of Sin, and Juſtification of a Sinner, tho' Repentant, is not, by Vertue of ſuch Repentance alone, due to the Sinner, nor attainable by him:</hi> To evince the Truth of this Poſition: I lay down this Principle engrafted in Man's Natural Reaſon: <hi>(viz.)</hi> That an Injury, or Injuſtice done to another, requires a condign ſatisfaction, or repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be made to the Party injur'd, before the Party injureing can juſtly challenge a Remiſſion, or quitting of Scores for the injury done; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the greater the injury, the greater ſtill is the ſatisfaction due: Nor is it to the purpoſe, That the Party injur'd is not in neceſſity, or want of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction equivalent to the damage ſuſtain'd by the injurie, for ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction obligatory ariſeth not from want or indigency in the Party in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd, but from the juſt Propriety and Right he retains to what is his own. Neither is it material in the ſtrictneſs and exigency of Juſtice, That the party injureing repents him of the injury done; for Repentance is no recompence to the damnify'd perſon, and therfore notwithſtanding ſuch Repentance, the obligation of ſatisfaction, or indemnification remains due to the party injur'd. I alſo lay down this other Principle acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by all, That an injury, or injuſtice, being an uſurpation of anothers good and right, takes its ſpecies and degree of Malignity from the worth and value of the good and right uſurp'd; and when the worth is Infinite, the injuſtice is ſo too. Now Sin, as it includes a diſobedience and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance to the known Will and Law of God an Infinite good, carries along with it an infinite degree of Injuſtice, and on its part deſpoils the Almighty of his Soveraignity and Right of being the firſt Original on which all things depend, and laſt end to which all things ought to be referr'd: For which infinite Injuſtice done to God by Sin, Man a finite and limitted thing can make no condign ſatisfaction. From theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Principles, is neceſſarily concluded my firſt Poſition. <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Remiſſion of Sin, and Juſtification of a Sinner, tho' Repentant, is not by Vertue of ſuch Repentance alone due to the Sinner, nor at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable by him.</p>
            <p>My ſecond Poſition is, The Fruition of God in regard to Man, tho' of himſelf innocent, and free from Sin, is not by force or efficacy of ſuch innocence due to Man. Before I undertake to prove this Poſition, it is fitting I firſt advertiſe; your Query, as to this part of it, is bottomed on a falſe ſuppoſition <hi>(viz.)</hi> That there is extant a Perſon arriv'd to the uſe and maturity of Reaſon, wholly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, or miſlead in the Principles of Chriſtianity; yet without any malignity of Will, ſpotleſs and inculpable in the obſervance of the Law of Nature; for in reallity there is no ſuch Perſon. To make out this, I need only to appeal to the experience of your ſelf, and all Mankind, whether it be not true, That there is in Man's Nature, from his very Conception and Birth, propagated in him, and inherent to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40686:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him, a ſtrong Propenſion to Vice and Wickedneſs; and as ſtrong an Averſion from Vertue and Goodneſs, which Corruption of human Nature is termed original Concupiſcence, and Injuſtice. And tho' this depravation doth not diſcover it ſelf in Infants, by reaſon of the Organs of the Body, on which the uſe and exerciſe of the rational Faculties of the Soul depend, are not qualify'd and diſpos'd in Infants for ſuch exerciſes. Yet ſo ſoon as theſe Impediments in the Organs ore removed, and Man by degrees arrives to the uſe and liberty of his Will and Reaſon in diſcerning Good and Evil, we manifeſtly and daily ſee, infected and vitiated Nature, hurried by the corrupt Inclinations radicated in it, without any new addition or change made in the Soul it ſelf, or its inclinations, willfully, and not by force or compulſion, breaks forth like an Ulcer into all Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and when let looſe and comply'd with vents it ſelf in Murders Rapines Brutalities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Overturns the Laws of God and Nature, and unhindges the whole frame of human Life and Converſation. Can this Malignity of Will, this rooted Concupiſcence and Injuſtice, be otherwiſe than odious to God, the Juſt, the Good, the Perfect? Is it not reaſonable, That as vitiated Man is averſe from Righteouſneſs, ſo the Righteous God ſhould be averſe from him? Is this then that ſpotleſs Innocence, and Integrity ſuppos'd in the Perſon repreſented in the Query, ſuch as may challenge the Frution of God in Glory? Surely no. But waving this groundleſs and deluſive Suppoſition, I ſtill aſſert; The Frution of God in Glory, in regard to Man even of himſelf innocent and free from Sin, is not by Force or Efficacy of ſuch Innocence, due to Man, nor attainable by him; to evince this Truth, I form this Argument; Nothing is due to nothing, or attainable by nothing; For from nothing comes nothing; And Worth or Merit is poportioned to Beeing. But Man is of himſelf nothing. Seeing all he is, all he has, and all he does, or can do, is by the free Guift and Participation of God his Creator, on the Influence of whoſe mere Bounty his whole Exiſtence entirely depends. Conſequently tho' Man ſhould have, and retain the pretended Innocence and Integrity wherein he was Created, and ſhould fully diſcharge his Duty in obſervance of the Law of Nature imprinted in him, nevertheleſs, God the whole and ſole Owner both of Man and his Operations, may if he ſo pleaſe, without any Reſemblance of Injuſtice, terminate his Bounty; And either annihilate Man by ſubtracting from him a further influence of Beeing, and ſo reduceing him to what he was at firſt, Nothing; or continue him, as without Guilt, ſo without Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the ſame State wherein he Created him, without any new addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Perfection or Happineſs; For an Enteity or Beeing by mere Bounty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40686:3"/>
and Participation, ſuch implies (as I may term it,) a nullity of Self-Right to any farther Augmentation. Furthermore, God is an infinite and unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted good, and the fruition of him in Glory is of infinite and unlimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted value, but it involves a contradiction, that a finite and limitted thing, as Man and his Operations are, ſhould by any proper worth or merit, purchaſe or claim as due an infinite and unlimitted good, as the fruition of God is; for a finite merit, and an infinite reward bear no proportion. It follows then, the fruition of God in Glory is not due to Man by force or vertue of any whatſoever ſelf Innocence or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in him. If it be objected, Man's Soul is naturally Immortal, and its rational Faculties, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Underſtanding and Will tend to the Fruition of God as their immortal ſpecifick object and end. The Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tends to God as the Origin of Truth: The Will tends to God, as the Origin of Goodneſs; there ſeems then due to the Immortality of Man's Soul the fruition of God, the Immortal Fountain of truth and goodneſs, due not by merit, but by the preſcript of Nature, and right of Creation. It is Anſwer'd, Man's Soul is ſaid to be natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly immortal in this Senſe; that abſtracting from the Body, it has not intrinſick to it any Principles of corruption, that is, any material humours or qualities repugnant and deſtructive to each other, and thereby producing Mortality; but it is not immortal in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, as if it had of it ſelf, and from its own nature ſome ſtability or immortality of exiſtence independent on the Will and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of its Creator, on account of which alone Man might claim as his due, the fruition of God by any right deriv'd from his Nature; ſuch an immortality the Soul of Man has not; his very being a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture excludes him from it; and there is nothing more con-natural to a Beeing by Participation, than a Non-ſelf-right to any thing. If it be ask'd, Why did God Create Man; yet render his end and happineſs neither due to him, nor attainable by him? It is Anſwer'd, Tho' the end and happineſs of Man being the fruition of God, an infinite good be neither due to Man, nor attainable by any ſelf merit inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence or induſtry in Man: Nevertheleſs, this end and happineſs of Man is attainable by ways and means agreeable to the Wiſdom of God, and commenſurate to his end.</p>
            <p>Wherfore my third Poſition is, Salvation as it imports Remiſſion of Sin, and fruition of God, is not abſolutely unattainable by Man. To prove this, I Argue; There is nothing whereby to render the benefit of Man's Salvation unatain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but either ſome limit or deficiency of power and goodneſs on God's part in conferring this benefit, or want of capacity on Man's part in receiving the benefit; not the firſt, ſeeing all the Attributes of God are, as his Eſſence, of infinite Perfection, and accordingly his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40686:3"/>
power and goodneſs unlimitted and indificient; Nor the ſecond; ſeing Man is ſuſceptable of any grace or favour whatſoever may conduce to the well Beeing of his Nature. Therfore Man's Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not abſolutely unattainable.</p>
            <p>My fourth Poſition is; It is moſt expedient, that remiſſion of Sin, and fruition of God ſhould be attainable by the interpoſition of one Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator between God, and Man Jeſus Chriſt, true God and Man. To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and render rational this Poſition, Note, It is Man did, and doth commit Sin, and it is Man ſtands liable to ſatisfaction for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury done to God by Sin; (as hath been ſhewn in the firſt Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) And becauſe the injury done to God an infinite good, by Sin, is infinite, the ſatisfaction ought alſo to be ſo; but Man, a Creature, can make no ſuch ſatisfaction, (as hath been likewiſe ſhewn in the ſame Poſition.) That therefore there might be one who was Man, and could make an infinite ſatisfaction for the Sin of Man, it was expedient, God ſhould become Man, and thus be a fit Mediator between God and Man. Again, It is acknowledg'd, the end and happineſs of Man is the Fruition of God, an infinite God (as is intimated in the Objection to the ſecond Poſition) It is likewiſe acknowledg'd, no Merits, Innocence, or Induſtry in Man can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as means to attain to this end (as is alſo intimated in the ſame Poſition.) That therfore Man might not be deſtitute, and fruſtrated of the end and happineſs for which he was Created; It was expedient the Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs ſhould provide means whereby Man might attain to his end, means commenſurate, and proportioned to the end; theſe means are the infinite merits of Chriſt Jeſus our Mediator, God and Man. Notwithſtanding all which, I do not ſay, That becauſe neither Remiſſion of Sin, nor Fruition of God is due to Man, or attainable, either Remiſſion by ſole Repentance in a Sinner, or Fruition by proper merit in an Innocent; therfore it was of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity to the Salvation of Man, God ſhould become Man, and thereby mediate between God and Man; for God as Suprem Lord, unaccountable to any for the diſpenſations of his bounty, or determinations of his Will, might, if he had ſo pleaſed, <hi>Gratis,</hi> without regard to any purchaſe or merit, both have remitted the Sin of Man, and beſtow'd the Fruition of himſelf upon Man, as an effect of his ſole Benignity and Goodneſs: But, I ſay, it was moſt expedient and congruous to the manifeſtation of the pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude both of God's Mercy and Juſtice, that the Remiſſion of Sin, and the Fruition of God, two infinite Benefits, ſhould be conferr'd on Man by the infinite merits of Chriſt Jeſus our Mediator.</p>
            <p>Now my fifth Poſition is, There is <hi>de facto</hi> a Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man, Chriſt Jeſus, who being God, became Man,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40686:4"/>
Dy'd upon the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thereby Merited and Purchas'd for Man a Right and Title to the Remiſſion of Sin, and Frution of God. I ſhall prove this important, Poſition, by ſuch Rational Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and Motives of Credibility, as may be convincing to an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Underſtanding. The firſt Evidence or Motive, is taken from the Plenitude of the Mercy and Juſtice of God, (ſo often inculcated and now repeated.) Man by Sin had committed an infinite Injury, and by that Injury was obnoxious to infinite Miſery: This Miſery ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him the Object of no leſs then an infinite Compaſſion and Mercy, the ſole Property of God an infinite Good, This infinite Compaſſion and Mercy could be in nothing extended and manifeſted more effectually than for God to become Man; and for the redreſs of Mans irreparable Miſery, to render himſelf miſerable. Again, God as he is Merciful, ſo is he Juſt; The Juſtice of God called for Satisfaction, condign Satisfaction for Mans injuſtice done by Sin, But (alas) worthleſs Man could (as is ſaid before) make no ſuch Satisfaction, therfore God becoming Man, and Dying for Man, made Satisfaction in the utmoſt rigor of Juſtice for the Sin of Man. Moreover the End and Happineſs of Man (as hath been often ſaid) is the Fruition of God an infinite Good; but Man was deſtitute of proper Self Merit, and means whereby to attain to this ineſtimable End, (as hath been likewiſe ſaid and proved) therfore God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Man, merited and purchas'd, for Man, what before ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely tranſcended his Reach. The ſecond Evidence or Motive of Credibility, is taken from the Stupendious Miracles done by Chriſt whilſt on Earth, to prove himſelf to be God, and his Doctrine or Goſpel Suprem and Divine; Miracles infinitely above the compaſs of any created Strength or Induſtry, and only Commenſurate to a Divine Power; As are raiſing the Dead to Life, healing the Lame, giving Sight to the Blind, curing the Sick of naturally incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſtempers, and all theſe ſuddenly, and by his ſole Touch, Word, or Command; As likewiſe are, Caſting out of Devils Aſſwaging Tempeſts, Walking upon the Sea, as upon Dry Land, Feeding to Overplus Five Thouſand Perſons, with Five Loaves of Bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As alſo are Manifeſtations of the Secret of Mens Hearts; a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of all things both preſent and diſtant, both paſt and to come. Miracles done in the Preſence, ſome of Thouſands, ſome of Hundreds, and all of a ſufficient Number of Eye-Witneſſes; Miracles undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by his then extent moſt malicious Adverſaries; Miracles uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally atteſted, and the Memory of them perpetuated by the unanimous harmony of Perſons and Records of all Ages. Theſe Miracles, I ſay, are ſuperabundant Evidences and Motives of Credibility, that Chriſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40686:4"/>
our Saviour is God, and his Doctrine or Goſpel Divine. The Third rational evidence of motive or Credubility, is taken from the wonderful Propagation of the Goſpel of Chriſt. None who judge by Reaſon, or even common Senſe, can imagine, That a few in number, and thoſe poor illeterate and deſpicable Perſons, (as were all the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt, ſent and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion'd by him to Preach his Goſpel) delivering a Doctrine not only above the reach of natural Science, or Knowledg, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant and deſtructive to the Maxims of the World, and Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhments of the Fleſh, ſhould nevertheleſs contrary to all Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral or Carnal Intereſt, ſuperiour to all Human difficulties, and invincible to all Oppoſitions, ſpread and dilate this Doctrin through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World, and tranſmit it indelible to all future Ages. None, I ſay, of common Reaſon or Senſe, can imagin ſuch a Doctrine, ſo deliver'd and propagated, could have any other than God for the Author. The fourth and laſt rational evidence or motive of Credibility, is taken from the Purity, Sanctity, and Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of manners contain'd in the Principles, and relucent in the Practiſe of the true Chriſtian Religion, and remonſtrating the ſame to be no leſs than Divine. We find Man's contaminated Nature tranſported and hurry'd with a ſtrange deluge, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuoſity to Vice and Sin, to Pride and Self-conceit, to Avarice, to Luſt, to Intemperance, to Rage, to Fraud, to Malice, to Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and all kind of Immorality: Which contamination of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture receives no ſmall addition from the Temptations and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of the World. It was therfore highly neceſſary, there ſhould be an Antidot to the Poiſon, healing Remedies to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and a Medicinal Law to repreſs the Miſdemeanors, and rectify the Diſorders of deprav'd Nature: It was neceſſary, I ſay, there ſhould be apply'd to our Pride and Self-conceit, Humility and Submiſſion; to our Avarice, Poverty of Spirit; to our Luſt, Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency and Chaſtity; to our Intemperance, Faſting and Abſtinence; to our Rage and Paſſion, Meekneſs and Patience; to our Fraud, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity; to our Malice, Charity; to our Injuſtice, Righteouſneſs; and to the Temptation of the World, a Contempt and Diſregard of it in what it Alienates the Heart from God its Creator: That thus Man from Vicious, might become Vertuous; his Soul adorn'd and perfected with Holineſs of Life; his corrupt Nature reclaim'd, and himſelf led, as it were, by Manuduction to his laſt end. Theſe are the bleſſed fruits and effects, ſpringing from Goſpel Dictates, which if impartially conſider'd, give a Moral aſſurance they flow from a Divine Fountain and Original. It may be Objected, There are Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40686:5"/>
of Perſons believing and profeſſing Chriſtianity, upon whoſe Lives and Manners theſe Goſpel dictates, work no ſuch effects, as are here mention'd. It is anſwered; there are indeed too too many Profeſſiors of Chriſtianity, whoſe wicked Practiſes are little anſwerable to the Purity and Sanctity taught and known in the Goſpel Dictates; however this Wickedneſs of Manners proceeds not from any deficiency in the Dictates, but from a delinquency in the Profeſſors, which Profeſſors therfore may fitly be ſtiled, as to point of Practiſe, no Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>My laſt concluſive Poſition is, There is neceſſary to Salvation, as it imports Remiſſion of Sin and Fruition of God, a Faith in Chriſt, as the indiſpenſable Condition, or means introductive and Applicative of his Merits and Mercies to Man. To prove my poſition, I argue thus; Upon the Reception of a Benefit <hi>Gratis,</hi> and by Benevolence beſtowed on a Rational Creature; the very Law of Nature dictates there is required and due, an Owning or Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be made of the Benefit; Yes, and a Love to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd by the Receiver to the Benefactor. But it is impoſſible, ſuch an Acknowledgment ſhou'd be made, or Love render'd, without a previous Knowledg of the Benefit received; For no Man can either Acknowledg, or Love he knows not what, conſequently ſeing the Remiſſion of Sin and Fruition of God, are, (as hath been proved in the firſt and ſecond poſition) Benefits purely <hi>Gratis,</hi> and by Benevolence beſtowed by God on Man, there is indiſpenſably required and due to God, from Man, a reciprocal and grateful Acknowledgment of, and love for theſe precious Benefits. But this Acknowledgement can never be made, nor love render'd without a Knowledg of the Truths and Miſteries including the Benefits. And this Knowledg can never be attain'd by natural Science, but only by Faith. For Faith is defined to be a Knowledg of certain Truths or Myſteries diuinely reveal'd, relating to Mans Salvation, and aſſented to becauſe ſo reveal'd, tho' not demonſtrable by deduction, from natural Cauſes and Effects. Thus then Faith is indiſpenſably neceſſary to Salvation. Hence this main Article, concerning the neceſſity of Faith, hath been conſtantly Preached, Divulged, and received in all Ages and Places, when, or where ſoever the name of Chriſtian hath gained admittance. And all the Arguments and Motives of Credibility brought in the fifth Poſition, to prove the Doctrine or Goſpel of Chriſt to be True and Divine, prove alſo this Article of the neceſſity of Faith to be True and Divine, as being an Eſſential Part of the ſame Doctrin or Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40686:5"/>Having thus given a diſtinct Proof to each particular Clauſe, or matter contain'd in the general Aſſertion <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Salvation, as it imports Remiſſion of Sin, and fruition of God is not due to Man, nor attainable by him, otherwiſe than by a Faith in one Mediator Chriſt Jeſus; and that therefore there actually is ſuch a Mediator, and ſuch a Faith: I ſhall now make a diſtinct Anſwer to diverſe particular Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections implicitly included in your general Query. And firſt it is Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, God has indu'd Man with Reaſon, on account of which, Man is ſaid to be a rational Creature, and therefore it is contradictory to his very Nature, to give an Aſſent, or Belief to the truth of any Propoſition (ſuch as is every Article of Faith) tranſcendant to his Reaſon; for this would be for Man to deveſt himſelf of his Nature. It is Anſwer'd, If by the word <hi>Reaſon</hi> be meant that rational Power or Faculty in the Soul, term'd the Underſtanding, by which Man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the truth or falſity of a thing: It is indeed contradictory to Man's Nature to give an aſſent without ſuch a faculty, to any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; For this would be to underſtand without an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But if by the word <hi>Reaſon,</hi> be meant a rational Evidence, Cauſe or Motive of Credibility, why a Man gives an aſſent to the truth of any Propoſition; It is not contradictory, but moſt agreeable and conſonant to Man's Nature, to give an aſſent upon ſuch rational Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to any Propoſition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is Objected, When God Created Man, he gave him a faculty of Reaſon, whereby to arrive to the knowledge of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, by the footſteps of Nature, and imprinted in his Soul a Law of Morality, whereby to diſtinguiſh Good from Evil. Now it ſeems propoſterous, and deſtructive to the eſtabliſh'd order and frame of Nature, That God ſhould inſtitute a new Law, and require from Man a belief of it, and ſubmiſſion to it, The truth of which nevertheleſs tranſcends the ability of human Reaſon, traceing the footſteps of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to comprehend. It is anſwer'd, Man may arrive to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of a truth by two ways. The one is by an intrinſick demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration from Natural cauſes to their effects; and this knowledge is term'd natural Science: The other is by an extrinſick Manifeſtation, or Revelation of a Proponent, or Atteſtant, and herein the aſſurance of ſuch a knowledge of truth, is proportion'd to the Credit and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Proponent; And in ſhort, if God, who is truth it ſelf, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts and reveals a truth, the knowledge and aſſurance of ſuch a truth, is ſuperiour to all human or natural Science: This knowledge is what we term Faith. Nor is this knowledge of God, and his Law, arriving to Man by Revelation, any wiſe propoſterous or deſtructive to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40686:6"/>
we have of him, and his Law, drawn from the footſteps and impreſſions of Nature; but rather a ſupply to the deficiency of ſuch natural knowledg; for God is immenſe, and his ways inſcrutable, and none can by inferences and conſequences drawn from the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Nature, comprehend the total, either of what God is, or what he may require of us: Indeed, ſeing the bounties and benefits con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd by God on his Creatures, are the meer effects of his own free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, the very freedom and liberty of his Will in conferring, or not conferring theſe bounties and benefits, implies an impoſſibility of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the knowledg of them, before, or otherwiſe, then as he free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſes to reveal and manifeſt them; And as it is the height of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to ſay, God within the verge of Nature has done ſo much, he cannot do more; ſo is it the height of Arrogance (after he hath reveal'd and manifeſted the effects of his Will above the verge of Nature) to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm he hath not done more. Thirdly, It is Objected, That the rational dences and Motives of Credibility, ſpecify'd in the fifth Poſition, tho' they afford a Moral certainty of the truths reveal'd by Chriſt, yet not amounting to a ſcientifical Demonſtration, they ſeem diſproportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and inſufficient to cauſe or produce that aſſurance of aſſent chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leng'd by Faith: It is Anſwer'd, The ſpecify'd Motives of Credibility, are only the inſtrumental cauſes productive of Faith, (as tools in the hands of the Artificer) But the effecient cauſe producing an aſſurance of Aſſent to Divine Revelations or matters of Faith, is the veracity of God the Revealer, into which veracity, Faith (as the effect into its adequat cauſe) is finally reſolv'd and terminated. Fourthly, It is Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, An excluſion of an Innocent from the Fruition of God, his final end and happineſs, is a Puniſhment inflicted without a fault, and a cruelty incompatible with Divine Juſtice. It is Anſwer'd, An Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of Man however innocent and inculpable from the Fruition of God, an happineſs which neither by the right of Nature was due to him, nor which by any merit of his he could ever deſerve, cannot be term'd or eſteem'd a Puniſhment at all, either for, or without a fault, much leſs a cruelty incompatible with Divine Juſtice; for every Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is properly a ſubtraction of a benefit or happineſs from a culpable or guilty perſon; to which happineſs the guilty perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his guilt had ſome juſt propriety and right, and which right he juſtly forfeited by his guilt. Now an Excluſion of Man from the Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of God, is no ſuch thing, but only a pure Negation, or Non-conferring of a free guift or benovolence, to which Man however ſuppos'd innocent, neither has, nor ever could, have, any juſt proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or right; (as hath been more at large already prov'd in the ſecond Poſition) wherfore God may without any pre-ſuppoſition of Fault
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40686:6"/>
on Man's part, or imputation of cruelty and injuſtice on God's part, exclude Man from the fruition of himſelf, as a benefit or happineſs to which Man has no imaginable juſt Title or Claim; Nevertheleſs it may be granted, that a Perſon Innocent and free from Sin (if any ſuch had been) would not be liable to the horrid tortures, torments and flames, inflicted by the Judgment and Vengeance of God, on willful and malicious Sinners, for thoſe alone are juſtly Condemned to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Extremity, of an unhappy and miſerable Beeing, who to Sin have abandoned God, the ſole Fountain of well-Beeing. And in this ſenſe, it is moſt true, that regarding the above named Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and their Cauſe, there is none puniſhable who is not culpable. Fifthly, it is objected, to what purpoſe, and with what appearance of Juſtice, has God in ſo many Ages, Created and fixed in the World ſo many Perſons, who yet he knew neither would nor could ever attain to their natural End, and final Happineſs? Were it not better ſuch Perſons never had been? It is anſwered, (over and above what hath been already ſufficiently ſaid, and proved concerning this matter) A Beeing even in a condemned Sinner, is preferable to no Beeing, as far as his Beeing is the work of his Creator, for it is ſimply better to be ſomething than nothing; but the diſmal Miſeries and Torments attending the Sinner and annex'd to his Crime are no poſitive Beeing, but a privation of well-Beeing, The ſole effect and product of Malice and Sin. And as to the purpoſe or deſign God has in the Creation of Man, whether Good or Evil; It is for the Manifeſtation of his Soveraignity and Glory of his Attributes; He beſtows upon ſome, Bleſſings Temporal and Eternal, for the Manifeſtation of his Mercy; He inflicts upon others Puniſhments Temporal and Eternal for the Manifeſtation of his Juſtice; He grants to ſome, the Fruition of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, a Benefit above what they deſerve; He excludes others from the ſame Fruition, a Benefit they do not deſerve; Thus, he is Good to all, but unjuſt to none; he extends or limits the effects of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and goodneſs, according to the meaſure of his own Will, but ſtill without injuſtice to any: To illuſtrate this point, God might, if he would; have Created thouſands of Worlds beſides this, and in each World millions of Men; but he has not done it; muſt we then ſay, This poſſible Maſs of Worlds and Men, may juſtly accuſe God of Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and Injuſtice, in giving to this ſingle World an actual Beeing, and leaving all the reſt in the Abiſs of their own Nothing? Certainly No. And as God the Soveraign Lord hath amongſt his Works on Earth, made ſome irrational Creatures, as Stones, Plants, Brutes, without dignifying of them (as he hath Man) with the noble faculties of Will and Reaſon; becauſe it ſo pleaſed him; yet without any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40686:7"/>
injuſtice to the irrational Creatures themſelves; ſo the ſame Soveraign Lord hath amongſt the number of Mankind, in all Ages, deſtin'd and elected, ſome to the everlaſting fruition of himſelf, an happineſs they could not juſtly demand; And excluded others from the ſame fruition an happineſs they could not juſtly require; And this God, the Juſt, the Good, Will, becauſe he Will; and to conclude, It is true, God cannot Will, but what is Juſt and Good; but it is likewiſe true, what he Will is therfore Juſt and Good, becauſe he Will; for the Will of God is the Supream and Unaccountable Rule both of Juſtice and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>You add in the cloſe of your Query, That what you ſaid of an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believer may proportionably be adapted to an erroneous Believer; and you are in the right; for no Faith, and a falſe Faith, are equally Pernicious; the reaſon is, becauſe Faith applicative of Chriſt's Merits to Man's Juſtification, takes not its vertue and efficacy from the force or ſtrength of Perſwaſion in the Believer, but from the worth and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the Miſteries believ'd; ſo that when Faith is not uniform, and correlative to the integrity of its Object, being all, and every reveal'd Miſtery, each of which is influential to Juſtification, ſuch a Faith looſeth its applicative Property, and becomes abortive, fruitleſs, and deluſory.</p>
            <p>Thus, I hope, I have given you ſatisfaction to each particular Clauſe contain'd in your general Query: Now I wiſh the effect may corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond to the good Intention herein of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your well-meaning Friend and Servant, <hi>J. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40686:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
